Finding Aid for Irene Ellis Murphy papers, 1917-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Irene Ellis Murphy papers 1917-1984
Murphy, Irene Ellis, 1900-
851917 Aa 2
Birmingham, Michigan, businesswoman, Democratic Regent of the University of Michigan; contain materials relating to her life and interest in the Philippines, especially during the administration of Frank Murphy, during World War II, and during the presidency of Ferdinand Marcos; papers relating to her interest in University of Michigan history; and photographs.
3.2 linear feet
502 MB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Irene Murphy (donor no. 4132 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1964.
The collection is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Irene Ellis Murphy was born in Connersville, Indiana in the years 1900. She received her M.A. from the University of Michigan in 1928 and began a career as a social worker with the Detroit Department of Public Welfare and the Council of Social Agencies. She worked here until 1945.
In 1929, she had married J. Harold Murphy, the brother of then Detroit Mayor Frank Murphy. When Murphy left to become Governor General of the Philippine Islands (1933-1935), he took many members of his family with him. From her stay in the Philippines in the mid-1930s, Irene Murphy would develop a life-long interest in the people and politics of the Islands.
Upon encouragement of Frank Murphy who headed the Philippine War Relief organization, Irene Murphy in 1945 accepted the position of field representative and assistant to the executive director. From 1946 to 1950, she worked with the Secretariat of the United Nations, and from 1951 to 1954, she was an advisor on Philippine cottage industries with the United States Foreign Operations Administration. Her work in this capacity led Irene Murphy to establish her own business back in Michigan in which she imported and merchandised Asian village products.
Irene Murphy was also a loyal Democrat, who served her party and her alma mater, the University of Michigan, with election to the Board of Regents, serving from 1957 to 1966.
Irene Murphy died July 25, 1989.
The Irene Murphy collections has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Murphy family; University of Michigan Board of Regents; Philippines interests and activities; Other topics; Scrapbooks and clippings; Sound recording; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Birmingham (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.); Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Murphy, Irene Ellis, 1900-; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan--Songs and music.; Businesswomen--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobiles--1941-1950.; Children.; Children playing.; Children's parties.; Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Harbor Beach.; Families.; Funeral rites and ceremonies.; Harbor Beach (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Horseback riding.; Interiors.; Japan.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Murphy, George, 1897-1961.; Murphy, Irene Ellis, 1900-; Murphy, Marguerite.; Murphy, Sharon Ann.; Philippine War Relief of the United States.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Recreation.; Soldiers--American--Philippines.; Travel.; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; Weaving.; Women.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Murphy, Irene Ellis, 1900-; Philippines--Economic conditions--1946-1986.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1917-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (postcards) (Box 1)
  - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1984 (Box 1)
- Murphy family
  - Teahan, Mary Aurora (adopted daughter of William and Marguerite Murphy Teahan) (Box 1)
  - Frank Murphy and family papers (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Board of Regents
  - Paper concerning the selection of a president for the University of Michigan 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - "Regents of the University of Michigan; Profiles and Selection/Election Procedures" by Irene Murphy and Frederick C. Matthaei, Jr. August 1983 and related background materials (Box 1)
  - Papers re University of Michigan song, "Laudes Atque Carmina" (Box 1)
  - Philippine Center, possibility of one being established at the U-M 1973 (Box 1)
  - Inaugural address 1958 (Box 1)
  - Campaign miscellanea (Box 1)
- Philippines interests and activities
  - Philippine War Relief (of the United States) Inc.
    (Murphy was field representative and assistant to the executive director of the Philippine War Relief organization)
    - Papers 1944-1947 (Box 1)
      (many of them addressed to Frank Murphy who was a director of the Philippine War Relief organization, regarding the work of Irene Murphy with the organization)
    - Report on Field Operation for the Year of 1946 (Box 1)
    - Final report April 30, 1949 (Box 1)
  - US Foreign Operations Administration, advisor on Philippine cottage industries
    - Paper: "The Philippine Program for Cottage Industries: An Evaluation" 1953 and related materials (Box 1)
  - "Persons from Michigan and/or the University of Michigan who helped build the democratic institutions of the Republic of the Philippines" (Box 1)
  - Taruc (Luis Taruc), materials regarding, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Araneta, (Salvador Araneta), correspondence and materials regarding, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Aquino (Benigno Aquino), materials regarding (Box 1)
  - Manglapus (Raul Manglapus), materials regarding (Box 1)
  - Jilson (Lilia Lopez Jilson), materials regarding (Box 1)
  - Lopez (Eugenio Lopez, Jr.), materials regarding and martial law in the Philippines (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Other topics
  - Vietnam War (letters to the editor and position paper) (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks and clippings
  - Personal and biographical, Frank Murphy and other members of the Murphy family, activities in the Philippines, etc. (Box 2)
    (the scrapbooks have been put into folders)
- Sound recording
  [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
  - Irene Murphy interviewed by Voice of America, 1959 June 08, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [851917-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Alan Strong from Voice of America interviews Irene Murphy. She discusses her stays in the Philippines, including her work as a social worker and in nurturing village industries after World War II.)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize photographs in box 4)
  - Homes (Box 3)
  - Murphy, Frank
    - Funeral (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Murphy, George, family (Box 3)
  - Murphy, Harold and Irene, family (Box 3)
  - Murphy, Irene
    - As a child (Box 3)
    - Informal (Box 3)
    - Japan (Box 3)
    - Philippines
      - Informal (Box 3)
      - With others
        - Banquets, meetings, formal groups (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Portraits (Box 3)
    - With Sharon (Box 3)
  - Murphy, Sharon Ann
    - Informal (Box 3)
    - Portraits (Box 3)
      (see also oversize portrait in box 4)
    - With others (Box 3)
  - Murphy and Ellis families and friends (Box 3)
  - Philippines
    - Children (Box 3)
    - Independence Day 1946 (Box 3)
    - People and groups (Box 3)
      (see also oversize group photo in box 4)
    - Weaving (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Teahan, Marguerite Murphy (Box 3)
  - Photograph album (Box 4)
    (includes photos from her activities in the Philippines)